Chapter 62. The dart.
A word concerning an incident in the last chapter.
According to the invariable usage of the fishery, the whaleboat pushes off from
the ship with the headsman or whale killer as temporary steersmen and the
harpooner or whale fastener pulling the foremost ore, the one known as the
harpooner ore. Now it needs a strong nervous arm to strike the first iron
into the fish. For often in what is called a long dart, the heavy implement
has to be flung to the distance of 20 or 30 ft. But however prolonged and
exhausting the chase, the harpooner is expected to pull his ore meanwhile to
the uttermost. Indeed, he is expected to set an example of superhuman activity to
the rest, not only by incredible rowing, but by repeated loud and intrepid exclamations.
And what it is to keep shouting at the top of one's compass while all the other
muscles are strained and half started.
What that is none know but those who have tried it. For one, I cannot ball
very hardily and work very recklessly at one at the same time. In this straining
balling state, then with his back to the fish, all at once the exhausted
harpooner hears the exciting cry, "Stand up and give it to him." He now has to
drop and secure his ore, turn round on his center halfway, seize his harpoon
from the crotch, and with what little strength may remain, he essays to pitch
it somehow into the whale. No wonder, taking the whole fleet of whalemen in a
body, that out of 50 fair chances for a dart, not five are successful. No wonder
that so many hapless harpooners are madly cursed and disr. No wonder that
some of them actually burst their blood vessels in the boat. No wonder that some
sperm whalemen are absent four years with four barrels. No wonder that to
many ship owners whailing is but a losing concern. For it is the harpooner
that makes the voyage. And if you take the breath out of his body, how can you
expect to find it there when most wanted? Again, if the dart be successful, then at the
second critical instant, that is when the whale starts to run, the boat header
and harpooner likewise start to running for and aft to the imminent jeopardy of
themselves and everyone else. It is then they change places, and the headsman,
the chief officer of the little craft, takes his proper station in the boughs of the boat.
Now I care not who maintains the contrary, but all this is both foolish
and unnecessary. The headsman should stay in the boughs from first to last.
He should both dart the harpoon and the lance, and no rowing whatever should be
expected of him, except under circumstances obvious to any fisherman.
I know that this would sometimes involve a slight loss of speed in the chase, but
long experience in various whalemen of more than one nation has convinced me
that in the vast majority of failures in the fishery, it has not by any means
been so much the speed of the whale as the beforeri exhaustion of the harpooner
that has caused them. To ensure the greatest efficiency in the dart, the
harpooners of this world must start to their feet from out of idleness and not
from out of toil.